<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY date "September 2007">
  <!ENTITY version "0.1.4">
  <!ENTITY application "TFLA-01">
]>
<article lang="en" id="index">
  
<articleinfo>
  <title>QPaMaT-Manual</title>
  
  <author>
    <firstname>Bernhard</firstname>
    <surname>Walle</surname>
    <affiliation>
      <address><email>bernhard.walle@gmx.de</email></address>
    </affiliation>
  </author>

  <pubdate>2008-12-07</pubdate>
  
  <releaseinfo>Version 0.5.4</releaseinfo>   
  
  <copyright>
    <year>2003-2008</year>
    <holder role="mailto:bernhard.walle@gmx.de">Bernhard Walle</holder>
  </copyright>

</articleinfo>



<sect1>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>The name</title>
    
    <para>First of all: What does this stupid name 
      <application>QPaMaT</application>
      mean? Well, it's an abbreviation -- the "Q" stands for Qt, the toolkit
      I used to build the application, "PaMaT" stands for "password managing
      tool". I liked this name because it rhymes to "Automat".</para>
      
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>History and Future</title>
    
    <sect3>
      <title>History</title>
      
      <para>Because QPaMaT is an open-source application, I want to write
        a bit about this history. A few years ago, I looked for a tool to
        store my passwords which is free and runs on Linux. I found many tools
        but they all didn't fit my requiremends, so I wrote my own one. I used
        Perl/Tk for that and it was done in a few days. Of course, the code was 
        not very good to maintain. But it worked
        for about two years (and, of course, it still works) without loosing
        any data. For encryption, I used <command>gpg</command>.</para>
        
      <para>The program had some small bugs and I liked a tree instead of a
        simple list for the sites. Perl/Tk has no tree widget, Tk is not what
        I expect from a modern user interface and Perl is no language for bigger
        programs (esp. GUIs). So I decided to re-implement my password tool from
        scratch. I wanted to learn Qt and improve my C++ programming skills.</para>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3>
      <title>Future</title>
      
      <para>Since QPaMaT does what I expect I don't plan to add lots of
        features in future. Of course, bugs will be fixed, translations
        and ports to other operating systems are welcome. And I plan to
        maintain QPaMaT in future.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Description</title>
    
    <sect3>
      <title>Basic usage</title>
      
      <para>QPaMaT is a tool to manage your passwords and other data such as
        customer numbers, corresponding URLs and so on. It has a simple 
        structure: On the left you see a tree which represents all your
        data. Each tree entry represends a sites (or a category with children
        that represents sites). So a category could be "Onlineshops", and a
        site could be "Amazon" or "Bookzilla", for example. On the right
        you find a list with key-value-pairs. Keys could be "password",
        "login", "URL", "account number". And the value is the corresponding
        value, of course. Each pair has a category: If it is a password, 
        it needs to be encrypted, a URL can be double-clicked to open a
        web browser and so on.</para>
      
      <para>Because QPaMaT is a tool to store passwords, it cannot store the
        data in a simple text file. The passwords have to be encrypted.
        QPaMaT uses the OpenSSL library for that task. This is a C library
        which is used by many programs (including the Konqueror web browser), 
        so it has proven to be mature, stable and secure.</para>
        
      <para>You can store the password file on the disk (well, on any path,
        so this includes network files, floppys, etc.) and you can additionally
        store the passwords (and only the passwords) on a memory card. The
        card must be a simple memory card which can be bought by electronic
        sellers such as Reichelt <ulink url="http://www.reichelt.de"></ulink>
        in Germany.</para>
      
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Features</title>
      
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Simple, fast and free program to store your passwords.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Generation of random passwords</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Checking of password quality, customizable dictionary.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Stores the passwords encrypted on the disk or on a smartcard.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Getting started</title>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Installation</title>
      
    <para>QPaMaT is very protable. It is written in C++ programming language
      using the Qt toolkit from Trolltech. This toolkit is avaiable for all
      major operating systems: Unix (including Linux, Solaris, HP-UX and
      many others) using X11, MacOS X and Microsoft Windows.</para>

    <para>QPaMaT also uses the OpenSSL crypto library which is available
      for much platforms, too.</para>
    
    <sect3>
      <title>Unix</title>

      <para>
        You have to have installed Qt4 on your computer. Qt3 does not work any more.
        If your distribution does not have Qt4 packages, get Qt4 from Trolltech
        and build it yourself. It's easy and described in the <filename>REAMDE</filename>
        file of the Qt distribution.
      </para>
      
      <para>First try to find a binary package for your Unix. If you run
        Linux, the chances are good. I create RPMs of every releases.
        So, just install the packages using the following command:</para>
        
      <para>
        <prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>rpm -Uvh qpamat-version-i586.rpm</userinput>
      </para>
        
      <para>If not, you need to compile it from source. Make sure that
        Qt is installed properly, including developer packages which
        contains the headers and the build tools like <command>qmake</command>.
        Also make sure that the environment variable <envar>QTDIR</envar>
        points to the right place, usually something like
        <filename>/usr/local/Trolltech/Qt-4.0.0</filename>. You also need to have OpenSSL
        installed, including header files.</para>

      <para>
        You have to set also the <envar>QMAKESPEC</envar> variable to a correct value,
        for example <filename>/usr/local/Trolltech/Qt-4.0.0//mkspecs/linux-g++</filename>.
        <command>qmake</command> must be in <envar>PATH</envar>. Normally, just
        include <filename>$QTDIR/bin</filename> in your <envar>PATH</envar> environment.
      </para>
        
      <para>You may edit <filename>qpamat.pro</filename> to change install
        location if you don't like <filename>/usr/local</filename>.
        To compile and install QPaMaT, run
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>qmake qpamat.pro</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>
        <prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>make</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>
        <prompt>$ </prompt><userinput>lrelease qpamat.pro</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>
        <prompt># </prompt><userinput>make install</userinput>
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Windows</title>

      <para>Just use the installer file which is available at the QPaMaT website.
        If you want to compile from source, you have to download the GPL version
        of Qt from the Trolltech website and basically perform the same steps as
        on Unix. The file <filename>WIN32.txt</filename> in the top-level
        directory of the source distribution contains some more hints.</para>

    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>First startup</title>
    
    <para>QPaMaT is multi-user aware. On operating systems with different
      users (such as Unix or Windows NT), each user has different settings.
      QPaMaT stores its settings in the home directory or in the
      Windows registry. On first startup with that account, QPaMaT asks
      you to enter the master password. This master password is used
      to encrypt all your other passwords. So be careful and choose a
      good password. If the password is too simple, QPaMaT declines it.
      If the password is accepted, you find a empty windows.</para>
  
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Normal usage</title>
    
    <para>You can now create your entries. On the left you see the
      "Sites" tree. Because you've not created any entries, there's no
      tree but a white area. If you right-click somewhere in this are,
      a menu opens. Choose <guimenuitem>Insert category</guimenuitem> and
      enter a name, e.g. "Onlineshops" and press the
      <keysym>Return</keysym> key. Now right-click on that item
      and choose <guimenuitem>Insert Item</guimenuitem>. Enter a name
      such as "Amazon".</para>
      
    <para>Of course, you can now enter some data. On Amazon, you usually
      have a e-mail address for login, a password and the URL. On the
      right, you see the list of key-valuie pairs. The list is empty but
      you fill it now. Click somewhere in the list with the right mouse
      button and choose <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem>. On the bottom,
      you can now edit the entry. Click on the combo box and choose
      "Username". The cursor is set in the <guilabel>Value</guilabel> text
      field. Enter your mail address. If you would like, you can change
      "Username" to "e-mail address" in the <guilabel>Key</guilabel> field.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Now enter a new item and choose "Password". Enter the password now
      in the <guilabel>Value</guilabel> field. You'll see that the password
      is not displayed. To get it, double-click the password in the list
      above. You can also copy it to clipboard by clicking on it with
      the middle mouse button or, if you have a two-button mouse, right click
      and choose <guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem>. After that, you can
      enter the URL as third entry. If you double-click the URL in the
      list, a browser will be opened to show the URL. You can change the
      browser in the preferences.</para>
    
    <para>After that, you want to save the data. Just choose 
      <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> and the
      data will be saved in a XML file in your home directory. You can
      change the location in the preferences.</para>
      
    <para>If you exit the application and start it again, just enter
      your password and you'll see that same screen as you saw it before
      you closed the application.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="config">
  <title>Configuration</title>
  
  <para>All configuration settings can be done by
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice></para>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>General</title>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enable AutoLogin on startup</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If this setting is active, the login dialog is shown
            on startup automatically. Otherwise, you have to
            choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Login</guimenuitem></menuchoice> manually.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data file location</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Location of the data file which is the XML file used
            to store the data (i.e. passwords, user names, etc.). Default
            ist <filename>.qpamat</filename> in your home directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Auto Text</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Text which is inserted automatically if you edit a key-value
            pair of the list and you choose a <guilabel>Type</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Passwords</title>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Generated passwords</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the length and the list of allowed characters for
            generated random passwords. You may also specify an external
            application (e.g. for pronouncable passwords) for generation.
            Externally generated passwords will be checked by the
            password checker, too.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Limits for password checker</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Set the limits when a password is treated as "weak" or
            "strong". The unit is the estimated number of days to crack 
            for a brute-force attack.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dictionary file</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The algorithm which calculates the password strength
            uses a dictionary file because it assumes that the hacker
            plans a dictionary-attack. Some files are distributed
            with QPaMaT. The format is simple: Each line contains a word
            and the dictionary is sorted according to the length. That
            increases the speed of the algorithm.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sort dictionary</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this function to sort the dictionary according to
            the length. The files supplied with QPaMaT are already sorted.
            Use this function for sorting your own dictionary files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Security</title>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cipher algorithm</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only change this if you know what you do. The 
            algorithms are provided by the OpenSSL library and the availability 
            is determined at runtime. You can read a file encrypted with 
            <emphasis>X</emphasis> only if the computer on which 
            you read it is able to handle algorithm <emphasis>X</emphasis>.
            </para>
          
          <para>Blowfish is a good choise because 
            it's free and available everywhere. IDEA is patended (but secure, 
            PGP uses it!) and AES (the successor of DES) is only available at 
            new versions of OpenSSL. Read a book about cryptography if 
            you're interested in this algorithms.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Auto logout after inactivity</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the application receives no mouse or keyboard events
            for the given amount of time, a logout if performed. If the data
            have been changed and needs saving, only a logout dialog is displayed.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  
    <sect2>
    <title>Smart Card</title>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Use a smartcard</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Determines whether a smartcard is used to store passwords.
            The passwords will be stored encrypted on the card and the
            location where they are stored is referenced in the XML files.
            QPaMaT uses normal memory cards.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Card has write protection</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use this if the card has a hardware write-protection. You
            have to enter the PIN before some data is stored. This feature
            is experimental since it doesn't work here, but I'm quite
            sure that this is a bug of the smartcard driver. However, I 
            recommend to buy normal memory cards without write protection
            since it does not give more security (reading cannot be protected
            this way).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>CT-API chipcard driver </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the path to the chipcard driver. This is a dynamically
            loaded shared object file <filename>*.so</filename> on Linux,
            <filename>*.dll</filename> on Windows. The CT-API interface
            was created for the German health card, so it should be available
            for most hardware. For the wide spread Towitoko reader, check
            <ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/cprados/"></ulink> for
            Linux drivers.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Chipcard terminal port</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the port where your card reader is connected. Make
            sure that you have the right permission to access this port.
            Consult the manual of the driver for the correct port number.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Test</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Test your smartcard settings. Insert a card in the reader
            and click on this button. A dialog informs you about the result
            of the test.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Presentation</title>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hide passwords in the random password dialog</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Determines whether the password should be displayed as
            cleartext or hidden in the random password dialog. Choose
            "hidden" if you are in an unsave environment such at work
            or university.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Don't grab keyboard focus in the password dialog</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Normally, QPaMaT gabs the keyboard if a dialog is displayed 
            where the user should enter a password. This is fore security 
            reasons since it is more difficult for another applications to 
            read what you type in this text field. However, if you don't like
            this for usability issues, you can disable it here.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Printing fonts</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the fonts (including size) that are used for printing.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>System tray</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If this item is activated, a icon is shown in the system tray
            which allows the application to be hidden from task bar and
            desktop without being closed. To take effect, the application
            has to be restarted.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Start hidden</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Starts the application hidden. This option is only available if the
        system tray is activated. If you start the application, it minimizes
      into the system tray.
        </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
  
<sect1>
  <title>Command reference</title>
  
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Creates a new document to store passwords. It will be stored
          in the location you've set in the configuration. This function
          is useful if you want to delete all the passwords or you didn't
          create a document in the past.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Login/Logout</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are logged out, it offers the "Login" action:
          Asks you for the password and opens the current set of
          stored passwords. The data file which will be opened is set in the
          configuration dialog.</para>
        
        <para>Else, it offers the "Logout" action: 
          Closes the current set of stored passwords. If you didn't save
          it and you made changes, QPaMaT will ask you to do so. After that,
          all passwords are delected from memory (not form disk where they
          are encrypted, of course), so you need to Login again if you
          want access to your passwords.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Saves the current set of passwords on the hard disk. If you
          configured QPaMaT to use a chipcard, the passwords will be written
          to the card, too. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Exports the data. There are two export methods: XML and text.
        </para>
        
        <para>Exporting as text is mainly the same as "Save",
          but there are two differences: You can choose the file name directly
          in a file chooser, and if you configured QPaMaT to use a smart card, 
          this function stores the password in the XML file nevertheless. This
          function is useful for backup. </para>
        
        <para>Exporting as text exports the data in a clear text files, with
          readable passwords.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Prints our all entries as clear text. This is useful for
          "backup". Store this paper on a save place. Please recognize also
          if you use this function not at home but at work or university,
          the system administrator may have access to old print queue entries.
          So only use this function where you have a "secure environment" (whatever
          this means. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Exit the application. If some data was modified, you will be
          asked to save it before quitting.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Options</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Change password</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Changes the password for the current data. You have to enter
          the old password once and the new password twice. If you
          save the data, the change is applied.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Option</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Opens the settings dialog where you can configure
            the behaviour of OPaMaT, see <xref linkend="config" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Extras</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Random password</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Generates a random password. Of course, a computer cannot
          generate a <emphasis>really true</emphasis> random password,
          i.e. it's a pseudo-random password. So for really high security,
          don't use this function. But there is not a simple algorithm
          used such as the <function>rand()</function>-function in C.
          QPaMaT uses the random function of the OpenSSL library which
          is implemented by random functions of the operating system if
          it's available. This function was written for security applications
          (the encryption of your web browser may depend on the same
          function), so you can trust. On some systems, this function may
          not be available because the operating system lacks support.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Extras</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Show password strength</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Checks all passwords for its quality and shows the strength
          in the tree by four different indicators: <emphasis>red</emphasis>
          (insecury), <emphasis>yellow</emphasis> (quite secure),
          <emphasis>green</emphasis> (good security) and <emphasis>gray</emphasis>
          (no password stored in this item). Categorys show the weakest
          colour, so you can quickly check for weak passwords and change it.
          It's the same information as presented in the bottom right
          when you select a password in the list.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Extras</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Clear clipboard</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Convenience function to clear the content of the clipboard. This
          is useful if you copied a password and want to delete it in the
          clipboard for security reasons.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Opens this help document in a web browser (HTML format).</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>What's this</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Opens context help. The mouse cursor changes and lets you
          select a GUI element. A yellow window may appear and show some
          help on the item you've selected. But there's not for every item
          help available, this may change in future.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>About Qt</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Shows some information about Qt, the toolkit which was used
          to create this application. It's useful to get the version number
          of Qt.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Shows some information about the application, including the
          license and the version number.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Remote API (X11 only)</title>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>D-BUS?</title>
    
    <para>To remote-control <application>QPaMaT</application>, D-Bus is used.
      D-Bus is a simple, popular inter process communication mechanism on Linux
      and other Unix flavours.  For now, it doesn't exist on Windows and MacOS.
      This means that the D-Bus API is only available on Unix.
    </para>

    <para>For more information, see 
      <ulink url="http://dbus.freedesktop.org">http://dbus.freedesktop.org</ulink>
      or <ulink
        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D-Bus">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D-Bus</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Exported Services and Objects</title>

    <para>QPaMaT offers the service <literal>de.berlios.Qpamat</literal>.
      So far, the only object is <literal>/Qpamat</literal>. That
      object implements (apart from standard interfaces provided by the Qt API)
      <literal>de.berlios.qpamat.Qpamat</literal> following method:
    </para>

    <para>
      <funcsynopsis>
        <funcprototype>
          <funcdef><function>showHideApplication</function></funcdef>
          <paramdef></paramdef>
        </funcprototype>
      </funcsynopsis>
    </para>

    <para>That function takes no parameters. If the main window is hidden to
      the system tray, it shows the main window. Otherwise, i.e. if the main
      window is shown, it hides it. It performs the same action as clicking
      on the system tray icon.
    </para>

  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para><application>QPaMaT</application> only exports the function, it
      doesn't provide a capability to actually <emphasis>call</emphasis>
      that function. However, that's not necessary. You can use
      <application>dbus-viewer</application> which comes with Qt 4.2
      to interactively browse the exported services, objects and methods of an
      application.
    </para>

    <para>You can use <application>dbus-send</application> to call the only
      exported <literal>showHideApplication</literal> function. Just use
      following command:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
dbus-send --print-reply \
  --dest=de.berlios.Qpamat \
  /Qpamat \
  de.berlios.qpamat.Qpamat.showHideApplication
</programlisting>

    <para>This function is suitable to bind it to a key. For example, you
      can use the <application>xbindkey</application> tool which can execute
      arbitrary programs on key click. Most desktop environments like
      <application>KDE</application> or <application>Xfce</application>
      also have this capability without using external programs.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

</article>

<!-- vim: set sw=2 ts=2 et: -->
